Hello and welcome back to another
episode with It's Dr. Dan and today
we're going to be continuing to dive
into gas laws. So with gas laws, they
are all about how we can predict ideal
gases. So these are all about gases that
are that are behaving like particles
that are constantly in motion. they are
not interacting with each other. They
are experiencing different conditions.
So when we are looking at these
different conditions, these are things
that are actually measure measurable in
the lab. Meaning that we can try to
actually see what these are like. So
with all the previous things that we
were looking at before, they were going
from between an initial state of a gas
to a final state, meaning that we were
changing variables. So whether we were
changing pressure, changing volume,
temperature, moles, you saw things were
going from one thing to another. So when
we were looking at the ideal gas law,
one thing is very very different about
this and that there is no subscripts in
it. So what this particular formula does
is it refers to the current state or
conditions
of the gas that we are measuring. So
it's the current conditions. It has no
change involved. So no change. So being
that there is no change that means
there's no subscripts here. This is
something that's all about the variables
that are at hand. So what do we have
here? Well, the first one you can see is
that we have pressure. So we have P for
pressure and we have V for volume.
We have N for moles. So all of the
different variables that we saw before
and then we have T for temperature. Now
what units do these all have to be in?
Well, lucky for us, experiments have
been done in the past to help define a
specific constant that is unique to G to
the ideal gas law and that is the value
R. Now what this is is called the ideal
gas law constant. So we'll say it's the
ideal gas constant. Now for this
variable, it helps define what your
units are that you are dealing with in
your calculations. There are multiple
different types of ideal gas constants,
all with different units, but for the
purpose of these videos, we're going to
use the one where R is equal to 0.08206.
And with that the units are going to be
defined as well. So I'll move that over
here while we expand that just a little
bit.
So with that one what we are seeing is
that the units will be lers atmosphere
on top all divided by moles and by
Kelvin. So there's four units for the
specific constant. So helps us define
what our units are for all of the other
variables. Notice how through this we
have for pressure we have atmospheres
for volume we have liters for moles we
have the mole for temperature we have
Kelvin right all of these are defined
within the actual equation for ourselves
so it makes it a little bit of a check
and balance method to make sure do I
have everything defined properly. Now
the other thing about this v this
equation is that it can be easily
rearranged to for whatever our purpose
is. So what do I mean by that? Well all
of these different equations we can
rearrange them. So let's say for example
if I wanted to solve for any of the
different variables that we have have
had before. Well if I wanted to solve
for let's say uh volume we could go
through and do that for ourselves. So if
I wanted to get volume by itself, how
would we how do we do that? Well, we
would have to divide and get things by
itself. So if I divide pressure by both
sides, this will cause the pressure
units to cancel out on the left hand
side. And then we would have volume by
itself. So we'd have volume and our T
divided by P. So, and this is something
that can be done for any of the
variables that we have here. We're just
dividing and cancelling. So, we're going
to go through a bunch of examples to
show some different situations that we
can use the ideal gas law for. So, let's
dive in. So, for this one, the first
example that I have is I ask you, what
is the volume of one mole gas at STP?
Now, you might be asking yourself, what
is STP? What does that stand for? Well,
that's okay. So what STP stands for is
the standard temperature
and pressure. So this is a way for us to
derive important units. So for this one
the standard temperature is for us is
Kelvin. That comes from the Celsius to
Kelvin derivation
and pressure is 1 atmosphere. So let's
solve for volume using our equation. So
we're going to use the equation that I
showed before which was volume. So we
take the PV= NRT. We rearranged it
earlier to show that volume was equal to
NRT
/ P. And what we're going to do is also
going to write down all the other values
that we have. So we have temperature, we
have pressure, and then we have volume
or not volume, we have moles.
which is 1 mole. And what we are going
to be doing with all these is we're
going to plug in all of our variables
and we're also going to make sure that
everything properly cancels.
So when we plug these in for moles, we
have uh one atmosphere. Let's just move
this down.
Or sorry, moles, we have one mole.
For R, we have 0.08. 08206
L atmosphere mole Kelvin.
And notice how that's going to cancel
out the other units on the top here.
We'll plug in 273 Kelvin. So let's show
that for an example. So if I kind of
zoom in here for a second, notice how
moles will cancel moles and also Kelvin
will cancel Kelvin. And that's just on
the top of this. will also show that the
pressure is going to cancel out as well.
So one atmosphere is going to also
cancel out the one atmosphere which only
leaves liters is the one thing that's
not highlighted. So when we solve for
this we take 1 * 0.08206
* 273
solve that then divide by 1. Now when
that happens this is going to give us
our find our volume value. So we have a
volume of 22.4 L. Now is there anything
that's significant about this particular
value here? Well, one thing you might
notice is that this is in direct
relationship to one mole of gas. So what
it tells us is that one mole of gas is
equal to 22.4
L. So this is something that is an
extremely important
variable for ourselves to have on hand
because this is something called the
molar volume. Molar volume is a
conversion term that is derived from the
ideal gas law for any gas. So it doesn't
matter which one. It could be hydrogen,
bromine, CO2, oxygen, you name it. It's
for any gas. And this is a ratio where
one mole of all gases is equal to 22.4
L at STP. So this is a defined constant.
So write it down, have it for yourself.
This is called molar volume.
So it's something that could be very
useful in different calculations. So
let's try to use an example where we can
use that.
So, what volume does, if I have the
following question and I ask you, what
volume does 28.2 g of carbon dioxide
occupy at STP? So, the first thing
you're going to do is you're going to
make a little road map for yourself. And
in this one, I being that we start with
grams, well, how can we use that in an
ideal gas law? Well, if we kind of write
down our ideal gas law,
one thing that we can actually do is is
we can relate that to moles. The goal is
the mole whenever it comes to any of
these types of calculations. So, how do
we go from g to moles? Well, that's when
we're going to be using molar mass,
right? So molar mass
is all about g over moles. So in this
problem the first thing that we are
given is we're going to set up a little
conversion table for ourselves. We are
given 28.2
g of CO2.
So what is my molar mass of CO2? So we
can do a little calculation for
ourselves. So if we have one carbon
that's about 12.0 01 g. We have two
oxygens
and each one of those is 15.99
g each. So roughly this molecule is
around 44.0 g per mole.
So this is a conversion that we can
define and use. So when we plug this in,
we want to be able to cancel out g. So
that means moles will be on top. So this
tells us that 44 g is equivalent to one
mole of CO2.
So let's move that over for ourselves.
Move that down. Now when we are doing
this, g of CO2 cancels g of CO2.
Now what we're going to do is we want to
convert it to volume. Meaning we can use
the molar volume from that we defined in
our previous equation which if you
remember one mole of a of a gas so in
this case our gas is CO2 is equivalent
to 22.4
L of CO2. So once again we can double
check. Do our units cancel? Moles of CO2
cancels. Moles of CO2 they're gone. And
the only unit we have left is volume,
right? So when I solve this, we'll take
28.2
/ it by 44
* 22.4.
When we do that that calculation, what
we're going to end up getting is 14.5
L of CO2 is created from this problem.
So this is an example of how to use
molar volume, which is derived from the
ideal gas law.
So let's go back to how to use the ideal
gas law. So ideal gas law, there are
many different ways to use it. The
biggest one is you can use it to
identify different substances. Meaning
that you could use the ideal gas law to
find the molar mass, you can find
density, you can use it to find
molecular formulas, empirical formulas,
a lot of very useful piece of
information. So, with this one, I made a
little bit of a mystery for us to be
able to try to solve. We're going to
find out what the mystery gas is. So,
how can we do that? Well, the ideal gas
law can be used to find moles, meaning
that we can use that to figure out the
fingerprint of different gases. So, if I
have the following problem, I have 40.59
g of a sample of gas and it's found to
occupy 2.45 45 L at 235 Kelvin and it's
at a pressure of two atmospheres. I'm
like, whoa, that's a lot of information.
So, how did we go about trying to do
that? Well, let's highlight the
important pieces. So, we see we have 40.
59 g. So, with this, we have 40.59
g. So, that's a mass.
What other piece of information do we
have? We have that the gas occupies 2.45
45 L. So that is a volume.
We also have that it's at 235
Kelvin. So that is a temperature.
And then we also have that it's at a
pressure
of two atmospheres. So we also have a
pressure. Notice how when you are
writing these down, there are no
mentions of change occurring. So there's
no T2, no T1s that are occurring here.
It's a defined set of variables. Now
it's asking you what is the elemental
diatomic gas. So how can you identify
that? Well, what sets all molecules
apart is their molar mass. So we are
given a mass value. So what makes molar
mass? So molar mass is big m.
So molar mass what sets that apart? Well
big m is equal to in this case
is equal to g over moles.
So we are given the mass in this
particular problem right. So for this
piece of information we can um take that
mass that would go here. The one thing
that we need to try to calculate is the
number of moles. Well, how can we do
that? Well, if I take my PV= NRT,
our N value
is our missing mole value that we can
plug into this to figure out what the
identity is of this diatomic. So let's
rearrange the equation for ourselves. So
if I want to get moles by itself, I got
to divide both sides by RT.
This will cause R and T to cancel out on
the right hand side of the equation.
And what we are going to be left with is
that N is going to be equal to PV / RT.
So that's going to be our equation. So
what we're now going to do is plug in
our values for this. So if I have n and
that's equal to pressure. So pressure
was 2 atmospheres.
I have my volume which is 2.45 L
divided by R. So we're going to put that
in double parenthesis.
So that' be 0826
L atmosphere mole Kelvin and that's
going to be multiplied by the
temperature. That's 235
Kelvin. All right. So we're going to go
2 * 2.45
/
* 235.
Now one thing we can pay attention to is
did all of our units cancel? So we can
see atmospheres cancels,
lers cancels, and then we also had where
Kelvin cancels. So the only thing left
is moles. We're doing this to check to
make sure our units are correct. So when
we do this, we solve for N. And what
we're going to get is 0.254
moles of our mystery gas.
So now what we're going to do with this
value is that this is our blue value
that's going to get plugged in to our
equation from above. So what we're going
to do is we're going to take the mass
divided by the number of moles to solve
for our missing component.
So in the end what we are going to have
is our original mass. So let's put that
in orange.
So original value was 40.59
g was our mass and that's going to be
divided by
0.254
moles
and this is going to give us our molar
mass. So when you divide those two what
you're going to get for a molar mass is
159.8
8 g per mole.
All right. So, which datomic is it?
Which one do we have here when we have
159.8?
So, it's referring to datomics. So, what
are all of our datomics for ourselves?
Well, we got to try to remember a few
things. So, if you remember the acronym
have no fear of ice cold beer, that will
help you. So, that what they could be is
they could be H2
N2. So have no fear of ice cold
beer. So that's hydrogen gas, nitrogen
gas, I florine gas, oxygen gas, iodine
gas, chlorine, and bromine. Those are
our gases. Those are our choices. So
this is a pretty big mess. So, if I look
at H2, that one, if I times two of those
together, it's going to be roughly about
um about 2 g per mole. That's pretty far
away. If I look over to nitrogen gas,
that's about 28 g per mole. Oxygen is
going to be double 16, so 32 g per mole.
So, this is something that's going to be
really far down. Now, the other big
thing about this is I have them in order
also almost by weight. They're really
close. So, what's the biggest one out of
all these? Bromine, chlorine are the two
biggest. So, if we look at bromine,
well, one of them is 79.904.
But if I times that by two, that's going
to be about 159.8
g per mole. Now, does that match the
identity of our gas? And lo and behold,
it does. So our mystery gas in this case
is bromine. You did it, chemist. You
solved the mystery for the missing gas.
Congratulations.
So that is how we can do that, right?
We're solving it. Looking at the context
clues of our problem. It mentioned about
trying to solve figure out what that
missing gas was. So this is some
examples of how to use the ideal gas law
to help do your future assignments and
also to help teach you about this law.
It's very useful, especially when you
get the stoeometry. It helps you be able
to figure out different variables about
gases being generated in chemical
reactions as well. I hope this video
helped and I look forward to seeing you
all in the future. See you all later.
Bye now.